A Guide to the John B. Nelson papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA183
Rockefeller Archive Center
John B. Nelson papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1954-1974
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson, John B. (John Brockway)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA183
1 Cubic Feet 2 boxes and 2 volumes
Biographical/Historical note
John Brockway Nelson, researcher in animal pathology in the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Rockefeller Institute at Princeton, New Jersey from 1925 until 1950 and from 1950 until his retirement in June 1974 at the New York Laboratories. He worked primarily with diseases of the respiratory tract in animals and with latent viruses and tumors of mice. On his retirement, he presented without restriction, his professional correspondence, 1954-1974 to The Rockefeller University Archives.
Biographical note
1894 Born December 9 at Newburyport, Massachusetts
1917 B.S. (Microbiology) Massachusetts Agricultural College
1918 Harvard-M.I.T. School of Public Health
1918-1919 U.S. Army Medical Department
1919-1920 Public Service Laboratories (State Department of Health) Agricultural Experiment Station, University of Kentucky
1922-1923 A.M. (Bacteriology and Pathology) Harvard University Assistant to Dr. Bronfenbrenner, Harvard Medical School
1923-1924 Ph. D. (Bacteriology and Pathology) University of Missouri Assistant in Department of Animal Husbandry
1924 Instructor, Department of Microbiology, Univ. of Mass. (Fall term)
1925- Assistant, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research at Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, New Jersey
1929- Associate, RIMR at Princeton, N.J.
1938- Associate Member, RIMR at Princeton, N.J.
1942-1944 Consultant to the Secretary of War, Army Epidemiological Board, Commission on Tropical Diseases (field and laboratory work on bacillary dysentery); Member of special subcommission to India for study of enteric diseases; temporary consultant on diseases of laboratory animals, University of Chicago metallurgical laboratory (Manhattan Project)
1958 Griffin Award. Animal Care Panel, Chicago
1965- Emeritus, Rockefeller University, New York, N.Y.
1974 Closed laboratory. Retired
Member of: American Association Adv. Sci. Animal Care Panel, Society of Experimental Pathology, Society Bact., Society of Experimental Biology
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence, professional, and collected papers. Includes biographical material, bibliography and notes. Primarily a collection of professional correspondence.
John B. Nelson's chief scientific interest centered in naturally acquired diseases in laboratory animals, mainly mice and rats. The correspondence deals with strains of mice for experimental work, animal care facilities, care of experimental animals, publications, breeding, autopsies and tissue analyses.
The letter to George W. Corner gives a review of his scientific achievements up to 1959.
Arrangement note
Arranged in alphabetical order and in chronological order within name.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 N334
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Diseases; Pathology; Medicine, Preventive; Prevention and health; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Tumors in animals; Biology -- Research; Medical sciences; Medical research; Life sciences; Animals -- Diseases; Nelson, John B. (John Brockway); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Biographical material and early portrait (Box 1)
- Bibliography (Box 1)
- Scattered notes, 1959 January 21-February 26 (Box 1)
  - "Note for JBN/GRC paper scheduled 10/60 ACP St. Louis Techniques for breeding and maintaining SPF Swiss Mice." (Box 1)
  - Autopsies on healthy mice of a new colony, 1959 January 21, 1959 February 26 (Box 1)
  - Memorandum on Swiss mice, 1960 February 24 (Box 1)
  - Report on Special CFE Rats, 1969 December 16 (Box 1)
  - Lecture for Vincent Group Lab. at Rutgers University, 1959 April 29 (Box 1)
  - Murine Hepatitis: a review, undated (Box 1)
  - handwritten notes on definition of Tumor, undated (Box 1)
  - Untitled. On native diseases of laboratory animals chiefly mice, undated (Box 1)
  - Untitled. On chronic respiratory disease (CRD) in rats and mice, undated (September 24) (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - A (Box 1)
    - Acha, Pedro N., 3 items
    - Adams, Harriet Pettingell, 2 items
    - Adler, H.E. NY Acad of Sci. Conference on mycoplasmas, 1966 May 10-13; 5 items
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes reference to Theobald Smith.
    - Alpers, David, 2 items
    - Anderson, Marilyn J. Nat'l Acad, of Sci, 5 items
    - Andervont, H.B. Journal of the National Cancer Institute, 4 items
    - Arbuckle, L.D., 2 items
    - Armed Forces Institute of Pathology (J.M. Blumberg)
    - Armiger, Lois C., 6 items
  - B (Box 1)
    - Baernstein, H.D. Jr., 2 items
    - Bailen, Harold, 9 items
    - Baker, Dennis, 4 items
    - Bakke, John L., 2 items
    - Bang, Frederik B., 6 items
    - Banks, Donald R., 4 items
    - Barile, Michael F., 2 items
    - Barker, Rosalind, 5 items
    - Barksdale, Lane, 3 items
    - Barry, Guy T., 1964 May; 3 items
      Scope and Contents
      Deals with organizational changes at University Term. Memorial Research Center.
    - Bartlema, H.C., 3 items
    - Bayless, William A., 3 items. With enclosure.
    - Bekkum, D.W. van, 2 items
    - Benjamin, Stephen A., 4 items
    - Berg, Robert B., 2 items
    - Blieck, L. de, 3 items
    - Bostick, Warren L., 2 items
    - Boyer, Clyde I., 2 items
    - Bredt, W., 6 items
    - Bewer, N.R., 7 items
      Animal Care Panel - Office of the editor
    - Briggs, John D., 2 items
    - Bronk, Detlev W., 3 items
    - Brown, Arthur., 12 items
      USArmy, Virus and Rickettsia Division.
    - Brown, D.H., 1 item
      Animal Care Panel
    - Brown, Robert S., 2 items
    - Burkhart, Robert J., 5 items. 3 encl.
      NY Acad, of Sci. Program Chairman
    - Burns, Kenneth F., 5 items
  - C (Box 1)
    - Callis, J.J. Encl. from E.W. Smillie, 1957; 6 items
    - Campbell, C., 1 item
    - Campbell, Frank L., 1963; 1 item
      nomination to Advisory Council Inst, of Laboratory Animal Resources NAS
    - Carpenter, Charles P., 2 items
    - Carter, Philip B., 4 items
    - Carworth Farms Inc., 27 items
      Correspondents include: Ruth Michels, C.N. Wentworth Cumming, Dennis E.J. Baker J.W.; Cumming, Edith L.W. Cumming, Mildred Bevelander.
      Carworth Laboratories.
      Carworth Inc.
    - Cass, Jules S., 3 items
    - Chappell, W. Adrian, 2 items
    - Charles, R.T., 2 items
    - Charles River Breeding Laboratory signed Henry Foster, 16 items
    - Christensen, L.R., 3 items
      Includes "Methods for the identification of mycoplasmas"; personal letters in regard to changes in the research world and at RU.
    - Cieciura, S.J. Charles Pfizer and Co., 4 items
    - Clark, Paul F., 3 items
      Some anecdotal recollections of Theobald Smith
    - Cobb, Sidney, 2 items
    - Coffey, Julia M., 2 items
    - Cohen, Bennett J., 2 items
      Refusal of University of Mich, offer
    - Coltorti, Mario, 2 items
    - Conklin, Ruth E., 3 items
    - Conrad, Robert D., 1969 March; 6 items
      Lecture series University Calif., Davis
    - Cooper, John A.D., 2 items
      "Animal Quarters for Teaching and Research"
    - Corner, George W., 5 items
    - Correa, Walter Mauricio, 1 item
    - Cotchin, Ernest Nuffield Conference, 1966; 7 items
  - D (Box 1)
    - Darrow Laboratories, 2 items. With encl.
    - Davey, D.G., 2 items
    - Dienes, Louis, 2 items
    - Dill, David B., 6 items
      Army Chemical Center
    - Dolan, Margaret, M., 4 items
      Including paper on PPLO.
    - Dolman, C.E., 6 items
      On biography of Theobald Smith
    - Doloway, William C., 1956; 3 items
      Animal Care Panel 1956 Program Committee
    - Dubois-Prieels, A.M., 3 items
    - Duncum, Barbara Nuffield Foundation, 5 items
      Related Materials
      see also Cotchin, E.
    - Dunn, Thelma B., 4 items
  - E (Box 1)
    - Easterday, O., 2 items
    - Ebbesen, P., 11 items
    - Edward, A.G., 1968; 10 items
      Visiting lecture series. University Calif., Davis
    - Elias, Cloyd L., 4 items
    - Elliot, Stuart D., 3 items
      University of Cambridge visit
    - Erickson, Cyrus C., 3 items
      Am. Soc. Exp. Path. Nomination of Ira Singer. Nomination of Roy E. Ritts, Jr.
  - F (Box 1)
    - Fabricant, C.G., 3 items
    - Fallob, R.J., 2 items
    - Farrow, Wendall M., 4 items
    - Feinman, Marc., 1966; 2 items
      NY Acad. Sci. 1966 paper
    - Fernandes, Mario V., 2 items
    - Ferrigan, Lawrence W., 3 items
    - Fjelde, Audrey, 2 items
    - Flatt, Ronald E., 2 items
    - Flinn, Waldo. Account, 1960-1961 1965-1966; 4 items
    - Forbes, Martin, 2 items
    - Ford, Arthur C. Jr., 2 items
    - Foushee, Smith, 2 items
    - Franklin, John, 12 items
    - Frenkel, J.K., 4 items
    - Freundt, E.A., 4 items
    - Frey, Ruth D. Secretary for Dr. Rowe, 2 items
    - Friedman, Mark H., 3 items
    - Friedman, Robert M., 2 items
    - Friedmann, I., 3 items
    - Friend, Charlotte, Holograph
    - Fry, Virginia, 2 items
    - Furness, Franklin., 1960; 2 items
      NY Acad Sci.
  - G (Box 1)
    - Gailmor, William S., 2 items
      Veterinary Dispatch
    - Galton, Mildred M., 3 items
    - Garvey, Joseph J., 3 items
    - Gay, Frederick W., 1959; 4 items
      Includes comments on paper submitted to Infection and Immunity; 1959 PPLO conference NYAcad Sci.
    - Gianforte, Edward M., 2 items
    - Gledhill, A.W., 18 items
    - Gleiser, Chester A., 3 items
    - Godzik, Joseph R., 2 items
    - Goldfarb, Ronald H., 2 items
    - Goldforb, A.J., 5 items
      Soc. for Exp. Biol. and Med
    - Gowen, John W., 7 items
    - Graham, W.R., 4 items
    - Gray, Peter, 2 items
    - Gross, Paul, 2 items
    - Groupe, Vincent, 5 items
    - Grunberg, E., 2 items
    - Grunert, R.R., 2 items
    - Gude, James K., 6 items
    - Guerrero, Raul, 2 items
    - Guibor, Pierre, 2 items
    - Gupta, G., 2 items
      Isotope Committee
  - H (Box 2)
    - Habermann, Robert T., 9 items
    - Hancock, B.B., 2 items
    - Harris, Marvin M., 3 items
    - Hegner, James R., 2 items
    - Henthorne, Robert D., 8 items
    - Hill, Berton F., 11 items
    - Hinshaw, William R., 21 items
    - Hoffmann, Conrad E., 2 items
    - Hook, E.W., 2 items
      Strp. infection in colony of Swiss mice
    - Hudson, Leslie, 10 items
    - Huebner, Robert J., 1 item
    - Huttrer, Charles P., 3 items
      Opinion on Theodore Zucker request for research grant
  - I-J (Box 2)
    - Innes, J.R.M. (Hamish), 1954-1969; 23 items
    - Jackson, Georg J., 4 items
      Includes editorial opinion on Lerner mss for Experimental Parasitology.
    - Jacobs, Harry Lewis, 2 items
    - Jansen, J., 2 items
    - Jeffries, J.C., 2 items
    - Johnston, Evan V., 3 items
    - Jonas, Albert M., 2 items
    - Jones, Wallace A., 9 items
    - Jordan, Russell T., 5 items
    - Joshi, N.N., 7 items
  - K (Box 2)
    - Keiles, Elsa Orent, 3 items
      Includes recommendation on Dr. Niu grant application.
    - Keville, William A., 3 items
    - Kile, J.C., Jr., 1960 October 26; 2 items
      paper for Animal Care Panel
    - Kilham, Lawrence, 15 items
    - Kingrey, B.W., 2 items
    - Klein, Jerome O., 3 items
    - Koprowski, Hilary, 2 items
    - Kraft, Lisbeth M., 9 items
    - Kramer, John P., 7 items
    - Kueter, Kenneth E., 2 items
    - Kyker, Granvil C., 5 items
  - L (Box 2)
    - Lainson, R., 2 items
    - Lane-Petter, W., 2 items
    - Langer, Elinor, 3 items
    - Leash, Aaron M., 2 items
    - Lee, Milton O., 2 items
    - Lindsey, J. Russell, 4 items
      Includes comments on grant proposal.
    - Liu, Oscar, 6 items
    - Loeser, Charles N., 2 items
    - Lord, Geoffrey H., 1961 August; 8 items
      Am. Veterinary Med. Assoc. Symp
    - Lozano, Juan Mermejo, 6 items
    - Lutsky, Irving, 2 items
  - M (Box 2)
    - McAnuff, J.W., 1966 April; 4 items
      Nuffield Foundation. Symposium "The Pathology of Spontaneous Diseases in Rats and..."
    - McCay, CM, 2 items
    - McGhee, R. Barclay, 1961 January 30; 2 items
      Includes 1961 Jan. 30 letter regarding integration of zoology class.
    - Maciag, William J., 4 items
    - McMaster, P.D., 1957; 1 item
      disease in RI animals
    - Mahoney, William L., 2 items
      Estate of deceased sister
    - Manaker, Robert A., 2 items
    - Martin, J.H., 2 items
    - Maurer, Fred D., 2 items
    - Metzger, William I., 2 items
    - Mickelsen, Olaf, 2 items
    - Mitchell, Lawrence C., 2 items
      Conditions while at Prague Symposium
    - Mogabgab, William J., 2 items
    - Molomut, Norman, 9 items
      Waldemar Medical Research Foundation. Includes evaluation of grant request.
    - Moloney, William C., 2 items
    - Montgomery, Charles A., Jr., 2 items
    - Morris, J., 2 items
    - Morton, Harry E., 2 items
    - Moser, James H., 4 items
    - Mosesson, Norman D., 4 items
    - Mosley, James W., 5 items
    - Moulder, James W., 2 items
      Editorial opinion on paper by Dr. Tully submitted to Journal of Infectious Diseases
    - Mouriquand, Jacqueline, 11 items
    - Müller-Ruchholtz, W., 2 items
    - Murray, Edward, 2 items
    - Murthy, Y.K.S., 2 items
  - N-O (Box 2)
    - Niu, M. Chiang, 10 items
    - Niven, Janet S.F., 2 items
    - Organick, Avrum B., 14 items
  - P (Box 2)
    - Paget, G.E., 2 items
    - Passey, R.D., 2 items
    - Peters, Arthur C., 2 items
    - Peterson, Becky, With 3 encl.
    - Petherbridge, Wilbur R., 1962 March; 2 items
      Correction on Mar. 1962 Proc. Soc. Exp. Biol, and Med
    - Petri, Michael, 2 items
    - Piazza, Marcello, 25 items
    - Pitts, Grover C., 4 items
    - Poiley, Samuel M., 3 items
    - Pollard, Morris, 9 items
    - Powelson, Dorothy, 2 items
    - Purcell, Robert H., 4 items
  - R (Box 2)
    - Riet, F. van der, 5 items
    - Riley, Vernon, 4 items
    - Robnett, Aussey H., 2 items
    - Rokos, J., 4 items
    - Romaker, Robert, 8 items
    - Rosenthal, Melvin S., 4 items
    - Ross, Martin A., 2 items
    - Rowe, Wallace P., 2 items
    - Rozdilsky, B., 2 items
    - Rubin, B.A., 6 items
    - Ruchman, Isaac, 2 items
    - Ruebner, Boris H., 3 items
    - Rugh, Roberts, 7 items
  - S (Box 2)
    - Sackey, F.M.A., 2 items
    - Sacquet, E., 2 items
    - Sanders, Murray, 2 items
    - Sapanski, W.B., 1964 June 19; 2 items
      Metropolitan Animal Care Panel Address on Hepatitis
    - Schneiderman, Howard A., 3 items
      Recommendation of William Trager
    - Schwarz, Klaus, 2 items
    - Schwentker, Victor, 4 items
    - Seamer, John, 2 items
    - Senkus, Murray., 2 items
      Recommendation of Guy T. Barry
    - Seravelli, Egilde, 16 items
    - Shadduck, John A., 2 items
    - Sharp, John T., 4 items
    - Shelokov, Alexis, 3 items
    - Shepard, Maurice C., 2 items
    - Shimkin, Michael B., 2 items
      Editorial evaluation of Arison et al paper for Cancer Research
    - Siegmann, 2 items
    - Silliphant, W.M., 17 items
      Includes letter on retirement.
    - Simmons, M.L., 4 items
    - Simon, Harold J., 2 items
    - Simpson, William L., 2 items
    - Slanitz, Charles A., 1955 December 1-2; 4 items
      Program Animal Care Panel
    - Smith, Bruce H., 3 items
    - Soave, O.A., 10 items
      Editorial Board for Animal Care Panel
    - Solotorovsky, Morris, 2 items
    - Squire, Robert A., 6 items
    - Staats, Joan, 2 items
    - Stadler, Janice, 2 items
    - Stansky, Philip G., 2 items
    - Stevens, Russel B., 8 items
    - Stewart, Sarah E., 2 items
    - Stoliker, H.E., 2 items
    - Stone, H. Harlan, 3 items
    - Sullivan, Virginia, 2 items
  - T (Box 2)
    - Tajima, Yoshio, 2 items
    - Talbot, T.R., Jr., 2 items
    - Taranta, Angelo, 2 items
      Recommendation for Egilde Seravalli
    - Tarnowski, George S., 3 items
    - Taylor, Martha, 3 items
    - TenBroeck, Carl, 1 item; holograph
    - Terebessy, John, 1961 September; 6 items
      Travel arrangements to Prague
    - Tesouro, Miguel, 5 items
    - Thorp, W.T.S., 6 items
    - Tisdale, William A., 3 items
    - Theis, Gail, 2 items
    - Tobach, Ethel, 20 items
    - Tobian, Louis, 2 items
    - Trentin, John J., 2 items
    - Trexler, P.C., 3 items
    - Treon, Joseph F., 2 items
    - Tully, Joseph G., 8 items
  - U-V-W-X-Y-Z (Box 2)
    - Ushiba, Daizo, 3 items
    - Vainio, T., 2 items
    - VlÄek, A., 3 items
    - Vrolijk, H., 4 items
    - Wagner, Morris, 2 items
    - Waksman, Selman A., 2 items
    - Wallace, G.I., 3 items
    - Weidner, Earl, 3 items
    - Weihe, W.H., 2 items
    - Weisbroth, Steven H., 1 item
      Nomination of L.R. Christensen for Griffin Award
    - Weiser, Jaroslav, 14 items
    - Werderitsh, E.J., 4 items
    - Wheeler, Glynn P., 3 items
    - Wheeler, Margaret F., 2 items
    - Williams, Fletcher P., Jr., 10 items
    - Willoon, John E., 4 items
    - Wolf, Norman S., 2 items
    - Worden, Alastair N., 1968; 6 items
      social trip to England
    - Wright, Donald N., 2 items
    - Wunderlich, Gabriele, 2 items
    - Wynder, Ernest L., 2 items
- Collected Reprints
  Separated Materials
  Removed to RAC library 8/9/88.